<?xml version='1.0' encoding='ascii'?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM
	 "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc comments="no" ?>
<?rfc inline="no" ?>
<?rfc editing="no" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="2"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>


<rfc category="bcp"
  docName="draft-ietf-mtgvenue-iaoc-venue-selection-process-07"
  ipr="trust200902" submissionType="IETF" updates="" xml:lang="en">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="Venue Selection">IETF Plenary Meeting Venue Selection
      Process</title>

    <author fullname="Ray Pelletier" initials="R." surname="Pelletier">
      <organization>Internet Society</organization>
      <address>
        <email>rpelletier@isoc.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Laura Nugent" initials="L." surname="Nugent">
      <organization>Association Management Solutions</organization>
      <address>
        <email>lnugent@amsl.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Dave Crocker" initials="D." role="editor"
      surname="Crocker">
      <organization>Brandenburg InternetWorking</organization>
      <address>
        <email>dcrocker@bbiw.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Lou Berger" initials="L." surname="Berger">
      <organization>LabN Consulting, L.L.C.</organization>
      <address>
        <email>lberger@labn.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Ole Jacobsen" initials="O." surname="Jacobsen">
      <organization>The Internet Protocol Journal</organization>
      <address>
        <email>olejacobsen@me.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Jim Martin" initials="J." surname="Martin">
      <organization>INOC</organization>
      <address>
        <email>jim@inoc.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Fred Baker" initials="F.J." role="editor" surname="Baker">
      <organization />
      <address>
        <email>FredBaker.IETF@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Eliot Lear" initials="E." role="editor" surname="Lear">
      <organization>Cisco Systems GmbH</organization>
      <address>
        <email>lear@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date />
    <area>General</area>
    <workgroup>mtgvenue</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>The IAOC has responsibility for arranging IETF plenary meeting Venue
        selection and operation. This document details the IETF's Meeting Venue
        Selection Process from the perspective of its goals, criteria and
        thought processes. It points to additional process documents on the IAOC
        Web Site that go into further detail and are subject to change with
        experience.</t>
    </abstract>

  </front>

  <middle>

    <section anchor="Introduction" title="Introduction">
      <t>[[ED: The issue tracker for this document can be found at
	https://github.com/elear/mtgvenue/issues/.]]</t>
      <t>The IAOC has responsibility for arranging IETF plenary meeting venue
        selection and operation.  The purpose of this document is to
        guide the IAOC in their selection of regions, cities, and
        facilities, and hotels.  The IAOC applies this guidance at
        different points in the process in an attempt to faithfully
        meet the requirements of the IETF community.  We specify a set
        of general criteria for venue selection and several requirements for
	transparency and community consultation.</t>

	<t>It remains the responsibility of the IAOC to apply their best
	judgment. The IAOC accepts input and feedback both during the
	consultation process and later (for instance when there are changes in the
	situation at a chosen location). Any appeals remain subject to
	the provisions of <xref target="RFC4071">BCP101</xref>.  As
	always, the community is encouraged to provide direct feedback to the
	NOMCOM, IESG, and IAB regarding the discharge of the IAOC's
	performance.
	</t>
      <t>Three terms describe the places for which the IETF contracts
          services:<list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Venue:  "><vspace />This is an umbrella term for the
            city, meeting resources and guest room resources.</t>
          <t hangText="Facility:  "><vspace />The building that houses
            meeting rooms and associated resources.  It may also
            house an IETF Hotel.
	  </t>
          <t hangText="IETF Hotels:  "><vspace />One or more hotels, in close
            proximity to the Facility, where the IETF guest room allocations are
            negotiated and IETF SSIDs are in use.</t>
        </list></t>
<t>
      The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
      NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED",  "MAY", and
      "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in
      <xref target="RFC2119" />.
</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="objectives" title="Venue Selection Objectives">
      <section anchor="core" title="Core Values">
        <t>Some IETF values pervade the selection process. These often are
          applicable to multiple requirements listed in this document. They are
          not limited to the following, but at minimum include: <list
            style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Why do we meet?"><vspace />We meet to pursue the IETF's
              mission <xref target="RFC3935" />, partly by advancing the
              development of Internet-Drafts and RFCs. We also seek to
              facilitate attendee participation in multiple topics and to enable
              cross-pollination of ideas and technologies.</t>

            <t hangText="Inclusiveness:"><vspace />We would like to facilitate
              the onsite or remote participation of anyone who wants to be
              involved.</t>
            <t>Every country has limits on who it will permit within its
              borders. However the IETF seeks to: <list style="numbers">
                <t>Minimize situations in which onerous entry regulations
                  prevent participants from attending meetings, or failing that
                  to distribute meeting locations such that onerous entry
                  regulations are not always experienced by the same attendees </t>
                <t>Avoid meeting in countries with laws that effectively exclude
                  people on the basis of race, religion, gender, sexual
                  orientation, national origin, or gender identity</t>
              </list></t>

            <t hangText="Where do we meet?"><vspace />We meet in different
              locations globally, in order to spread the difficulty and cost of
              travel among active participants, balancing travel time and
              expense across the regions in which IETF participants are
              based.</t>

            <t hangText="Internet Access:"><vspace />As an organization, we
              write specifications for the Internet, and we use it heavily.
              Meeting attendees need unfiltered access to the general Internet
              and our corporate networks.  "Unfiltered access" in this
              case means that all forms of communication are allowed.
              This includes, but is not limited to, access to corporate networks
              via encrypted VPNs from the meeting Facility and Hotels, including
              overflow hotels. We also need open network access available at
              high enough data rates, at the meeting Facility, to support our
              work, including the support of remote
              participation. Beyond this, we are the first users of
              our own technology.  Any filtering may cause a problem
              with that technology development.  In some cases,
              local laws may require some filtering.  We seek to
              avoid such locales without reducing the
              pool of cities to an unacceptable level by stating a
              number of criteria below, one mandatory and others
              important, to allow for the case where local laws may
              require filtering in some circumstances.<xref
                target="MeetingNet" /></t>

            <t hangText="Focus:"><vspace />We meet to have focused technical
              discussions. These are not limited to scheduled breakout sessions,
              although of course those are important. They also happen over
              meals or drinks -- including a specific type of non-session that
              we call a "Bar BOF" -- or in side meetings. Environments that are
              noisy or distracting prevent that or reduce its effectiveness, and
              are therefore less desirable as a meeting Facility.</t>

            <t hangText="Economics:"><vspace />Meeting attendees participate as
              individuals. While many are underwritten by employers or sponsors,
              many are self-funded. In order to reduce participation costs and
              travel effort, we therefore seek locations that provide convenient
              budget alternatives for food and lodging, and which minimize
              travel segments from major airports to the Venue. Within reason,
              budget should not be a barrier to accommodation.</t>

            <t hangText="Least Astonishment and Openness:"><vspace /> Regular participants
              should not be surprised by meeting Venue selections, particularly
              when it comes to locales. To avoid surprise, the venue
              selection process, as with all other IETF processes,
              should be as open as practicable.  It should be possible
              for the community to engage early to express its views
              on prospective selections, so that the community, IAOC,
              and IAD can exchange views as to appropriateness long
              before a venue contract is considered.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="nonobjectives" title="Venue Selection Non-Objectives">
        <t>IETF meeting Venues are not selected or declined with the explicit
          purposes of:<list style="hanging">

            <t hangText="Politics:  "><vspace />Endorsing or condemning
              particular countries, political paradigms, laws, regulations, or
              policies.</t>

            <t hangText="Maximal attendance:  "><vspace />
	      While the IETF strives to be as inclusive as possible
              both online and in person, maximal
              meeting attendance in and of itself is not a goal. It
              would defeat a key goal of meeting if
              active contributors with differing
              points of view did not have the opportunity to resolve their
              disagreements, no matter how full the rooms.
            </t>
            <t hangText="Tourism:  "><vspace />Variety in site-seeing
              experiences.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

    </section>
    <section anchor="criteria" title="Meeting Criteria">
      <t>This section contains the criteria for IETF meetings.  It is
      broken down into three subsections: mandatory criteria,
      important criteria, and other considerations, each as explained
      below.
      </t>
    <section anchor="mandatories" title="Mandatory Criteria">
     <t>If criteria in this subsection cannot be met, a particular
       location is unacceptable for selection, and the IAOC MUST NOT 
       enter into a contract.  Should the IAOC learn that a location no
       longer can meet a mandatory requirement after having entered
       into a contract, it will inform the community and address the
       matter on a case by case basis.</t>
     <t><list style="symbols">
       <t>The Facility MUST be assessed to be able to provide sufficient
         space in an appropriate layout to accommodate the expected
         number of people to attend that meeting.</t>
       <t>The Facility and IETF Hotels MUST provide wheelchair access
	 to accommodate the number of people who are anticipated to
	 require it.</t>
       <t>The venue MUST provide unfiltered access to
	 the Internet, to the extent permitted by governing laws and
	 regulations.</t>
       </list>
       </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="importants" title="Important Criteria">
      <t>The criteria in this subsection are not mandatory,
              but are still highly significant. It may be necessary to
              trade one or more of these criteria off against others.
              A Venue that meets more of these criteria is on the
              whole more preferable than another that meets less of
              these criteria. Requirements classed as Important can
              also be balanced across Venue selections for multiple
              meetings.  When a particular requirement in this section
              cannot be met, the IAOC MUST notify the community at the
              time the venue is booked.  Furthermore, the IAOC is
              requested to assist those who, as a result, may be
              inconvenienced in some way.
      </t>
        <section title="Venue City Critera">
	<t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Travel to the Venue is acceptable based on cost, time, and burden
            for participants traveling from multiple regions. It is anticipated
            that the burden borne will be generally shared over the course of
            multiple years.</t>
          <t>The Venue is assessed as favorable for obtaining a host and
            sponsors. That is, the Meeting is in a location and at a price that
            it is possible and probable to find a host and sponsors. </t>
          <t>Travel barriers to entry, including visa requirements,
	    are unlikely to impede attendance by an overwhelming
	    majority of participants.</t>
          <t>Economic, safety, and health risks associated with this Venue are
            acceptable. </t>
	  </list>
	</t>
	</section>
	<section title="Basic Venue Criteria">
	<t>The following requirements relate to the Venue and Facilities.</t>
        <t>The IETF operates internationally and adjusts to
          local requirements. Facilities selected for IETF Meetings conform with
          local health, safety and accessibility laws and regulations. A useful
          discussion of related considerations in evaluating this criterion is
          at: <eref
            target="http://www.sigaccess.org/welcome-to-sigaccess/resources/accessible-conference-guide/" />
          <list>
            <t><list style="hanging">
                <t hangText="***  Editor's Note  *** "><vspace />In the spirit
                  of the 'international' focus, we need a comprehensive document
                  that is similar to the one cited, but without a national
                  focus. The current reference is US-specific. /d</t>
              </list></t>
          </list></t>

        <t>In addition:</t>
	<t>
	  <list style="symbols">
	  <t>There are sufficient places (e.g., a mix of hallways, bars, meeting
	    rooms, and restaurants) for people to hold ad hoc
	    conversations and group discussions in the combination of
	    spaces offered by the facilities, hotels and
	    bars/restaurants in the surrounding area, within walking
	    distance (5-10').</t>
          <t>The cost of guest rooms, meeting space, meeting food and beverage
            is affordable, within the norms of business travel.</t>
<!--          <t>The economics of the Venue are in line with expectations
            agreed between ISOC and the IAOC.</t> -->
          <t>The Facility is accessible by people with disabilities.
          While we mandate wheelchair accessibility, other forms are
          important, and should be provided to the extent possible,
          based on anticipated needs of the community.</t>
	  </list>
	</t>
	</section>
	<section title="Technical Meeting Needs">
	<t>The following criteria relate to technical meeting needs.</t>
	<t>
	<list style="symbols">
          <t>The Facility's support technologies and services -- network,
            audio-video, etc. -- are sufficient for the anticipated activities
            at the meeting, or the Facility is willing to add such
            infrastructure or these support technologies and services might be
            provided by a third party, all at no -- or at an acceptable -- cost
            to the IETF.</t>

          <t>The Facility directly provides, or permits and facilitates, the
            delivery of a high performance, robust, unfiltered and unmodified
            IETF Network.</t>

          <t>The IETF Hotel(s) directly provide, or else permit and facilitate,
            the delivery of a high performance, robust, unfiltered and
            unmodified Internet service for the public areas and guest rooms;
            this service is typically included in the cost of the room.</t>
	</list>
	</t>
	</section>
	<section title="Hotel Needs">
	<t>The following criteria relate to IETF Hotels.</t>
	<t>
	<list style="symbols">
          <t>The IETF Hotel(s) are within close proximity to each other and the
            Facility.</t>
          <t>The guest rooms at the IETF Hotel(s) are sufficient in number to
            house 1/3 or more of projected meeting attendees.</t>
          <t>Overflow Hotels can be placed under contract, within convenient
            travel time of the Facility and at a variety of guest room
            rates.</t>
          <t>The Venue environs include budget hotels within convenient travel
            time, cost, and effort.</t>
          <t>The IETF Hotel(s) are accessible by people with disabilities.
          While we mandate wheelchair accessibility, other forms are
          important, and should be provided to the extent possible,
          based on anticipated needs of the community.</t>
          <t>At least one IETF Hotel has a space for use as a lounge,
            conducive to planned and ad hoc meetings and chatting, as well
            as working online. There are tables with seating, convenient for
            small meetings with laptops. These can be at an open bar or casual
            restaurant. Preferably the lounge area is on the path between the
            meeting rooms and the hotel entrance, and is available all day and
            night.</t>
	  </list>
	</t>
	</section>
	<section title="Food and Beverage">
	<t>It is said that an army travels on its stomach.  So too
	does the IETF.  The following criteria relate to food and
	beverage.</t>
	<t>
	<list style="symbols">
          <t>The Venue environs, which includes both onsite, as well as areas
            within a reasonable walking distance or conveniently
            accessible by a short taxi ride or by local
            public transportation, have convenient and inexpensive
            choices for meals that can accommodate a wide range of dietary
            requirements.</t>
          <t>The Venue environs include grocery shopping that will accommodate a
            wide range of dietary requirements, within a reasonable walking
            distance, or conveniently accessible by a short taxi, bus, or subway
            ride, from the Facility and IETF Hotels.</t>
          <t>A range of attendee's health-related and religion-related dietary
            requirements can be satisfied with robust and flexible onsite
            service or through access to an adequate grocery.</t>
	  </list>
	</t>
	</section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="otherconsiderations" title="Other Consideraitons">
      <t>The following considerations are desirable, but not as
      important as the preceding requirements, and thus should not be
      traded off for them.
      </t>
          <t>We have something of a preference for an IETF meeting to
            be under "One Roof". That
            is, qualified meeting space and guest rooms are available in the
            same facility.</t>
          <t>It is desirable for overflow hotels provide reasonable,
            reliable, unfiltered Internet service for the public areas
            and guest rooms; this service is included in the cost of the room.</t>
          <t>It is desirable to enter into a multi-event contract with the Facility
            and IETF Hotels to optimize meeting and attendee benefits, i.e., reduce
            administrative costs and reduce direct attendee costs, will be
            considered a positive factor. Such a contract can be considered
            after at least one IETF meeting has been held at the Facility.</t>
	  <t>Particularly when we are considering a city for the first
	    time, it is desirable to have someone who is familiar 
	    with both the locale and the IETF participate in the site
	    selection process.  Such a person can provide guidance
	    regarding safety, location of local services, and
	    understanding best ways to get to and from the Venue, and
	    local customs, as well as identify how our requirements are
	    met.
	  </t>
    </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="roles" title="Venue Selection Roles">
      <t>The formal structure of IETF administrative support functions is
        documented in <xref target="RFC4071">BCP 101</xref>, <xref
          target="RFC4371" />, <xref target="RFC7691" />. The reader is expected
        to be familiar with the entities and roles defined by that document, in
        particular for the IASA, ISOC, IAOC and IAD. This section covers the
        meeting selection related roles of these and other parties that
        participate in the process. Note that roles beyond meeting selection,
        e.g., actually running and reporting on meetings, are outside the scope
        of this document.</t>

      <section title="IETF Participants">
        <t>While perhaps obvious, it is important to note that IETF meetings
          serve all those who contribute to the work of the IETF. This includes
          those who attend meetings in person, from newcomer to frequent
          attendee, to those who participate remotely, as well as those who do
          not attend but contribute to new RFCs. Potential new contributors are
          also considered in the process.</t>
        <t>Participants have a responsibility to express their views about
          venues early and often, by responding to surveys or other
          solicitations from the IAD or IAOC, and by initiating fresh input as
          the Participant becomes aware of changes in venues that have been
          reviews. This permits those responsible for venue selection to be made
          aware of concerns relating to particular locations well in advance of
          having entered into contract discussions.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="IESG and IETF Chair">
        <t>The Internet Engineering Steering Group (IESG) comprises the IETF
          Area Directors and the IETF Chair. Along with the IAB, the IESG is
          responsible for the management of the IETF, and is the standards
          approval board for the IETF, as described in <xref format="default"
            pageno="false" target="RFC2026">BCP9</xref>. This means that the
          IESG sets high level policies related to, among other things, meeting
          venues. The IETF Chair, among other things, relays these
          IESG-determined policies to the IAOC. The IETF Chair is also a member
          of the IAOC.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="The Internet Society">
        <t>With respect to IETF meetings, the Internet Society (ISOC): <list
            style="symbols">
            <t>Executes all Venue contracts on behalf of the IETF at the request
              of the IAOC</t>
            <t>Solicits meeting sponsorships</t>
            <t>Collects all meeting-related revenues, including registration
              fees, sponsorships, hotel commissions, and other miscellaneous
              revenues</t>
          </list> ISOC also provides accounting services, such as invoicing and
          monthly financial statements. </t>
      </section>

      <section title="IETF Administrative Oversight Committee">
        <t>The IETF Administrative Oversight Committee (IAOC) has the
          responsibility to oversee and select IETF meeting venues. It instructs
          the IAD to work with the Internet Society to write the relevant
          contracts. It approves the IETF meetings calendar. In cooperation with
          the IAD, the IAOC takes necessary actions to ensure that it is aware
          of participant concerns about particular venues as early in the
          process as is feasible.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="IETF Administrative Support Activity">
        <t>The IETF Administrative Support Activity (IASA) supports the meeting
          selection process. This includes identifying, qualifying and reporting
          on potential meeting sites, as well as supporting meeting Venue
          contract negotiation. The IETF Secretariat is part of the IASA under
          the management of the IAD. The IAD takes appropriate actions to
          solicit community input regarding both retrospective and prospective
          feedback from participants. </t>
      </section>

      <section title="IETF Administrative Director">
        <t>The IETF Administrative Director (IAD) coordinates and supports the
          activities of the IETF Secretariat, the IAOC Meetings Committee and
          the IAOC to ensure the timely execution of the meeting process. This
          includes participating in the IAOC Meeting Subcommittee and ensuring
          its efforts are documented, leading Venue contract negotiation, and
          coordinating contract execution with ISOC. The meetings budget is
          managed by the IAD.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="IAOC Meeting Committee">
        <t>The fundamental purpose of the Meetings Committee is to participate
          in the Venue selection process, and to formulate recommendations to
          the IAOC regarding meeting sites. It also tracks the meetings
          sponsorship program, recommends extraordinary meeting-related
          expenses, and recommends the IETF meetings calendar to the IAOC. The
          charter of the committee is at: <eref
            target="https://iaoc.ietf.org/committees.html#meetings" />.</t>
        <t>Membership in the Meetings Committee is at the discretion of the
          IAOC; it includes an IAOC appointed chair, the IETF Administrative
          Director (IAD), IAOC members, representatives from the Secretariat,
          and interested members of the community.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="steps" title="Venue Selection Steps">
      <t>The following sequence is used by the IAOC to select
      venues. Unless otherwise stated below, the IAOC may evolve these
      steps over time without updating this document.
      </t>

      
      <section title="Identification">
        <t>Four years out, a process identifies cities that might be candidates
          for meetings.  For example: <list style="letters">
            <t>The IAOC selects regions, cities, and dates for meetings.</t>
            <t>A list of target cities per region is provided to the
              Secretariat, with host preferences, if known.</t>
            <t>Potential venues in preferred cities are identified and receive
              preliminary investigation, including reviews of Official Advisory
              Sources, consultation with specialty travel services, frequent
              travelers and local contacts to identify possible barriers to
              holding a successful meeting in the target cities.</t>
            <t>Investigated cities and findings are provided by the Secretariat
              to the Meetings Committee for further review. Meetings Committee
              makes a recommendation to the IAOC of investigated/target cities
              to consider further as well as issues identified and the results
              of research conducted.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Consultation">
	<t>
	  The IAOC MUST consult the community about potential new venues
	  prior to them being booked.  The timing and means by which it does so
	  may vary over time, but MUST include references to any
	  notable travel risks.  The consultation may overlap
	  with the previous step (identification).
        </t>
        <t>For example:<list style="letters">
            <t>The IAOC asks the community whether there are any barriers to
              holding a successful meeting in any of the target cities in the
              set.</t>
            <t>Community responses are reviewed and concerns investigated by the
              Meetings Committee. The results together with recommendations for
              whether each city should be considered as potential meeting
              location is provided to the IAOC.</t>
            <t>The IAOC identifies which cities are to be considered as a
              potential meeting location.</t>
            <t>On a public web page, the IAOC lists all candidate cities, when
              community input was solicited, and if a city is to be considered
              as a potential meeting location.</t>
            <t>The Meetings Committee pursues potential meeting locations based
              on the posted list of cities that have been identified as a
              potential meeting locations.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Qualification">
        <t>Visit: <list style="letters">
            <t>Secretariat assesses "vetted" target cities to determine
              availability and conformance to criteria.</t>
            <t>Meetings Committee approves potential cities for site
              qualification visit.</t>
            <t>Site qualification visits are arranged by Secretariat and
              preliminary negotiations are undertaken with selected potential
              sites.</t>
            <t>Site qualification visit is conducted using the checklist
              along the lines of what is included in <xref
              target="checklist"/>; the site visit team prepares a site
              report and discusses it with the Meetings Committee.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Negotiation">
        <t>2.75 - 3 years out, initiate contract negotiations: <list
            style="letters">
            <t>The Meetings Committee reviews the Venue options based on Venue
              selection criteria and recommends a Venue to the IAOC. Only
              options that meet all Mandatory labeled criteria might be
              recommended.</t>
            <t>IAOC selects a Venue for contracting as well as a back-up
              contracting Venue, if available.</t>
            <t>Secretariat negotiates with selected Venue. IAD reviews contract
              and requests IAOC and ISOC approval of contract and authority for
              Secretariat to execute contract on ISOC's behalf.</t>
            <t>Contracts are executed.</t>
	    <t>The venue is announced.  At this time, the
	    announcement MUST include any notable travel risks or
	    references thereto.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Late Changes">
	<t>If at any time after a contract is signed the IAOC learns
	where a Venue's circumstances have significantly changed, such
	that the Important or Mandatory criteria can no longer be met,
	the IAOC MUST reconsider the selection.  A description of how
	reconsideration currently takes place is found in
	<xref target="flowchart"/>.  The IAOC will gauge the cost of
	making a change against the ability of the IETF to conclude a
	successful meeting, and make a final determination based on
	their best judgment. When there is enough time to do so, the IAOC
	is expected to consult the community about changes.
	</t>
      </section>

    </section>



    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This memo asks the IANA for no new parameters.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This note proposes no protocols, and therefore no new protocol
        insecurities.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Privacy" title="Privacy Considerations">
      <t>This note reveals no personally identifying information apart from its
        authorship.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>This document was originally assembled and edited by Fred Baker.
        Additional commentary came from Jari Arkko, Scott Bradner, Alissa
        Cooper, and other participants in the MtgVenue working
        group.</t>
    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>
    <!--references split to informative and normative -->
    <references title="Normative References">
      &RFC2119;
      <reference anchor="RFC2026"
        target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc2026">

        <front>
          <title>The Internet Standards Process -- Revision 3</title>
          <author fullname="S. Bradner" initials="S." surname="Bradner">
            <organization />
          </author>
          <date month="October" year="1996" />
          <abstract>
            <t>This memo documents the process used by the Internet community
              for the standardization of protocols and procedures. It defines
              the stages in the standardization process, the requirements for
              moving a document between stages and the types of documents used
              during this process. This document specifies an Internet Best
              Current Practices for the Internet Community, and requests
              discussion and suggestions for improvements.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="9" />
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2026" />
        <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC2026" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC4071"
        target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc4071">
        <front>
          <title>Structure of the IETF Administrative Support Activity
            (IASA)</title>
          <author fullname="R. Austein" initials="R." role="editor"
            surname="Austein">
            <organization />
          </author>
          <author fullname="B. Wijnen" initials="B." role="editor"
            surname="Wijnen">
            <organization />
          </author>
          <date month="April" year="2005" />
          <abstract>
            <t>This document describes the structure of the IETF Administrative
              Support Activity (IASA) as an activity housed within the Internet
              Society (ISOC). It defines the roles and responsibilities of the
              IETF Administrative Oversight Committee (IAOC), the IETF
              Administrative Director (IAD), and ISOC in the fiscal and
              administrative support of the IETF standards process. It also
              defines the membership and selection rules for the IAOC. This
              document specifies an Internet Best Current Practices for the
              Internet Community, and requests discussion and suggestions for
              improvements.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="101" />
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="4071" />
        <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC4071" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC4371"
        target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc4371">
        <front>
          <title>BCP 101 Update for IPR Trust</title>
          <author fullname="B. Carpenter" initials="B." role="editor"
            surname="Carpenter">
            <organization />
          </author>
          <author fullname="L. Lynch" initials="L." role="editor"
            surname="Lynch">
            <organization />
          </author>
          <date month="January" year="2006" />
          <abstract>
            <t>This document updates BCP 101 to take account of the new IETF
              Intellectual Property Trust. This document specifies an Internet
              Best Current Practices for the Internet Community, and requests
              discussion and suggestions for improvements.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="101" />
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="4371" />
        <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC4371" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC7691"
        target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc7691">
        <front>
          <title>Updating the Term Dates of IETF Administrative Oversight
            Committee (IAOC) Members</title>
          <author fullname="S. Bradner" initials="S." role="editor"
            surname="Bradner">
            <organization />
          </author>
          <date month="November" year="2015" />
          <abstract>
            <t>BCP 101 defines the start and end dates for the terms of IETF
              Administrative Oversight Committee (IAOC) members; these terms
              have proven to be impractical. This memo updates BCP 101 to direct
              the IAOC to establish more practical start and end dates for terms
              of IAOC members.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="101" />
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="7691" />
        <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC7691" />
      </reference>
      <!--
      <reference anchor="I-D.krishnan-ietf-meeting-policy">
        <front>
          <title>High level guidance for the meeting policy of the IETF</title>
          <author fullname="Suresh Krishnan" initials="S." surname="Krishnan">
            <organization />
          </author>
          <date day="8" month="July" year="2016" />
          <abstract>
            <t>This document describes a proposed meeting policy for the IETF
              and the various stakeholders for realizing such a policy.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft"
          value="draft-krishnan-ietf-meeting-policy-01" />
        <format
          target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-krishnan-ietf-meeting-policy-01.txt"
          type="TXT" />
      </reference>

-->
      <reference anchor="MeetingNet">
        <front>
          <title>IETF Meeting Network Requirements</title>
          <author fullname="Karen O'Donoghue" initials="K." surname="O'Donoghue" />
          <author fullname="Jim Martin" initials="J." surname="Martin" />
          <author fullname="Chris Elliott" initials="C." surname="Elliott" />
          <author fullname="Joel Jaeggli" initials="J." surname="Jaeggli" />
          <date />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="WEB"
          value="https://iaoc.ietf.org/ietf-network-requirements.html" />
      </reference>

    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">

      <reference anchor="RFC3935">

        <front>
          <title>A Mission Statement for the IETF</title>
          <author fullname="H. Alvestrand" initials="H." surname="Alvestrand">
            <organization />
          </author>
          <date month="October" year="2004" />
          <abstract>
            <t>This memo gives a mission statement for the IETF, tries to define
              the terms used in the statement sufficiently to make the mission
              statement understandable and useful, argues why the IETF needs a
              mission statement, and tries to capture some of the debate that
              led to this point. This document specifies an Internet Best
              Current Practices for the Internet Community, and requests
              discussion and suggestions for improvements.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="95" />
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3935" />
        <format octets="16639"
          target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc3935.txt" type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="I-D.barnes-healthy-food">
        <front>
          <title>Healthy Food and Special Dietary Requirements for IETF
            meetings</title>
          <author fullname="Mary Barnes" initials="M." surname="Barnes">
            <organization />
          </author>
          <date day="16" month="July" year="2013" />
          <abstract>
            <t>This document describes the basic requirements for food for folks
              that attend IETF meetings require special diets, as well as those
              that prefer to eat healthy. While, the variety of special diets is
              quite broad, the most general categories are described. There can
              be controversy as to what constitutes healthy eating, but there
              are some common, generally available foods that comprise the basis
              for healthy eating and special diets. This document provides some
              recommendations to meeting planners, as well as participants, in
              handling these requirements.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-barnes-healthy-food-07" />
        <format
          target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-barnes-healthy-food-07.txt"
          type="TXT" />
      </reference>
    </references>

    <section anchor="checklist" title="Site Qualification Visit Checklist">
      <t>
        This section is based on the PreQualification RFP, dated January
        23, 2016, which is available at
        <eref
            target="https://iaoc.ietf.org/meetings-committee/venue-selection.html"
            />.  The contents of the link may be changed as needed.
      </t>
      <texttable style="all" align="left">
        <preamble>Prequalification Specification</preamble>
        <ttcol></ttcol><ttcol></ttcol><ttcol></ttcol><ttcol></ttcol>
        <c>Meeting Dates:</c>
        <c>_________________</c>
        <c>Contact:</c>
        <c>_________________</c>
        <c>City:</c><c>_______________</c><c>Phone:</c> <c>_______________</c>
        <c>Venue Considered:</c> <c>_______________</c> <c> Email:</c> <c>_______________</c>
      </texttable>
      <!--<texttable style="all" align="left">
	  <preamble></preamble>
          <ttcol>Criteria</ttcol> <ttcol>Required</ttcol> 
          <c></c>          <c></c> 
          <c></c>          <c></c> 
          <c></c>          <c></c> 
          <c></c>          <c></c> 
          <c></c>          <c></c>
          <X postamble><X/postamble>
          </texttable> -->
      <texttable style="all" align="left" >
	<preamble>Meeting Space Requirements:</preamble>
        <ttcol>Purpose</ttcol>
        <ttcol>Space Required / Set</ttcol>
        <ttcol>sf/sm</ttcol>
        <ttcol>Room Assigned</ttcol>
        <ttcol>Daily Rate + (set-up rate)</ttcol>
        <ttcol>Days + (set-up)</ttcol>
       <ttcol>Total Price</ttcol>
       <c>Registration / Breaks** </c><c>1200 / custom</c><c>13,500 / 1254</c><c>Reg areas or foyers</c><c></c><c>6 + (1)</c><c></c>
       <c>NOC</c><c>25 / conf</c><c>1200 / 111</c><c></c><c></c><c>8 + (5)</c><c></c>
       <c>Terminal Room</c><c>75 / class</c><c>1350 / 125</c><c></c><c></c><c>7 + (1)</c><c></c>
       <c>Storage (if Reg &lt; 1000sf)</c><c></c><c>350 / 33</c><c></c><c></c><c>6 + (4)</c><c></c>
       <c>Plenary *</c><c>900 / theatre</c><c>8500 / 790</c><c></c><c></c><c> 2</c><c></c>
       <c>Breakout 1</c><c>80 / theatre</c><c>800 / 74</c><c></c><c></c><c> 6</c><c></c>
       <c>Breakout 2</c><c>100 / theatre</c><c>1000 / 93</c><c></c><c></c><c> 6</c><c></c>
       <c>Breakout 3</c><c>100 / theatre</c><c>1000 / 93</c><c></c><c></c><c> 6</c><c></c>
       <c>Breakout 4</c><c>150 / theatre</c><c>1400 / 130</c><c></c><c></c><c> 6</c><c></c>
       <c>Breakout 5</c><c>150 / theatre</c><c>1400 / 130</c><c></c><c></c><c> 7</c><c></c>
       <c>Breakout 6</c><c>200 / theatre</c><c>1900 / 177</c><c></c><c></c><c> 7</c><c></c>
       <c>Breakout 7</c><c>250 / theatre</c><c>2400 / 223</c><c></c><c></c><c>6</c><c></c>
       <c>Breakout 8</c><c>300 / theatre</c><c>2800 / 260</c><c></c><c></c><c>6</c><c></c>
       <c>Office 1 Registration</c><c>10 / conf</c><c>1000 / 93</c><c></c><c></c><c>6 + (4)</c><c></c>
       <c>Mtg Rm 1 (IAB)</c><c>8 / conf</c><c>350 / 33</c><c></c><c></c><c>6</c><c></c>
       <c>Mtg Rm 2 (ISOC1)</c><c>20 / conf</c><c>900 / 84</c><c></c><c></c><c>6</c><c></c>
       <c>Mtg Rm 3 (ISOC2)</c><c>20 / conf</c><c>900 / 84</c><c></c><c></c><c>6</c><c></c>
       <c>Mtg Rm 4 (IAOC / IAD)</c><c>15 / conf</c><c>650 / 60</c><c></c><c></c><c>6</c><c></c>
       <c>Mtg Rm 5 (NC)</c><c>15 / conf</c><c>650 / 60</c><c></c><c></c><c>6</c><c></c>
       <c>Mtg Rm 6 (NC IV)</c><c>Nov 5 / conf</c><c>150 / 14</c><c></c><c></c><c>6</c><c></c>
       <c>Mtg Rm 7 (40U)</c><c>40 / u-shape</c><c>1550 / 144</c><c></c><c></c><c>7</c><c></c>
       <c>Mtg Rm 8 (20U)</c><c>20 / u-shape</c><c>950 / 88</c><c></c><c></c><c>6</c><c></c>
       <c>Mtg Rm 9 (IESG)</c><c>16 / conf</c><c>800 / 74</c><c></c><c></c><c>6</c><c></c>
       <c>I: Postel Rec (WedPM)</c><c>40 / rec</c><c>400 / 37</c><c></c><c></c><c>1</c><c></c>
       <c>I: AC (Fri PM)</c><c>70 / custom </c><c>1700 / 158</c><c></c><c></c><c>1</c><c></c>
       <c>I: BoT (Sat / Sun)</c><c>70 / custom</c><c>1700 / 158</c><c>Same as AC</c><c></c><c>2</c><c></c>
       <c>I: Bot Lunch (Sat / Sun)</c><c>40 / banquet</c><c>550 / 51</c><c></c><c></c><c> 2</c><c></c>
       <c>I: Brfg Panel (Tue lunch)</c><c>150 / theatre</c><c>1400 / 130</c><c>Same as BO4</c><c></c><c>1</c><c></c>
       <c>I: Rec / Dinner (Fri)</c><c>50 / rec / ban</c><c>700 / 65</c><c></c><c></c><c>1</c><c></c>
       <c>I: Fellows Dinner</c><c>70 / rec / ban</c><c>900 / 84</c><c></c><c></c><c>1</c><c></c>
       <c>Lounge</c><c>50 / lounge</c><c>600 / 56</c><c></c><c></c><c>5</c><c></c>
       <c>Companion Rec</c><c>20 / rec</c><c>200 / 19</c><c></c><c></c><c>1</c><c></c>
       <c>Newcomers Rec</c><c>300 / rec</c><c>2500 / 232</c><c></c><c></c><c>1</c><c></c>
       <c>Welcome Rec</c><c>800 / rec</c><c>6400 / 595</c><c></c><c></c><c>1</c><c></c>
       <c>Hackathon</c><c>200 / class</c><c>3000 / 279</c><c></c><c></c><c>2 + (1)</c><c></c>
       <c>Bits n Bytes</c><c>700 / rec</c><c>7000 / 650</c><c></c><c></c><c> 2</c><c></c>

      </texttable>
      <t>
        <list>
          <t>* Breakouts 6 +7+8 (or some combination thereof) to be used as the Plenary as Plenary and Breakouts do not run simultaneously</t>
          <t>** Additional space required, not included in total meeting space</t>
          <t>Note: Prices quoted are those that will apply on the dates of the event and include all tax, services and fees</t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <texttable style="all" align="left" >
	<preamble>Accomodation:</preamble>
        <ttcol>Day/Date</ttcol> <ttcol> Total
        Rooms
        Required</ttcol> <ttcol>
        Desired
        Rooms at
        Primary
        Hotel</ttcol> <ttcol>
        Primary
        Hotel
        Availability</ttcol> <ttcol>
        Rate*
        Primary
        Hotel</ttcol> <ttcol>
        Desired
        Rooms at
        Overflow
        Hotels</ttcol> <ttcol>
        Overflow
        Hotel
        Availability</ttcol> <ttcol>
        Rate *
        Overflow
        Hotel</ttcol>

        <c>Total room nights</c> <c>5,250 (780 peak)</c> <c>4,245 (600 peak)</c> <c></c><c></c><c>1,005 (180 peak)</c> <c></c><c></c>
    <c>Monday</c> <c>5</c> <c>5</c> <c></c><c></c> <c>0</c><c></c><c></c>
    <c>Tuesday</c>   <c>15</c> <c>15</c> <c></c><c></c> <c>0</c><c></c><c></c>
    <c>Wednesday</c> <c>25</c> <c>25</c>  <c></c><c></c><c>0</c><c></c><c></c>
    <c>Thursday</c>  <c>50</c> <c>50</c> <c></c><c></c> <c>0</c><c></c><c></c>
    <c>Friday</c>    <c>185</c> <c>150</c> <c></c><c></c> <c>35</c><c></c><c></c>
    <c>Saturday</c>  <c>500</c> <c>400</c>  <c></c><c></c><c>100</c><c></c><c></c>
    <c>Sunday</c>    <c>770</c> <c>600</c>  <c></c><c></c><c>170</c><c></c><c></c>
    <c>Monday</c>    <c>780</c> <c>600</c>  <c></c><c></c><c>180</c><c></c><c></c>
    <c>Tuesday</c>   <c>780</c> <c>600</c>  <c></c><c></c><c>180</c><c></c><c></c>
    <c>Wednesday</c> <c>750</c> <c>600</c>  <c></c><c></c><c>150</c><c></c><c></c>
    <c>Thursday</c>  <c>700</c> <c>600</c>  <c></c><c></c><c>100</c><c></c><c></c>
    <c>Friday</c>    <c>370</c> <c>300</c>  <c></c><c></c><c>70</c><c></c><c></c>
    <c>Saturday</c>  <c>220</c> <c>200</c>  <c></c><c></c><c>20</c><c></c><c></c>
    <c>Sunday</c>    <c>100</c> <c>100</c>  <c></c><c></c><c>0</c><c></c><c></c>
          </texttable>


      <t>
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>Guest-room Internet, breakfast, 10% commission, all tax, service and fees are incorporated into the lodging rate.</t>
          <t>Guest-room rates quoted are those that will apply on the dates of the event.</t>
          <t>Attendees will book individually.</t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <texttable style="all" align="left">
        <preamble>Food and Beverage:</preamble>
        <ttcol>Purpose</ttcol><ttcol>When</ttcol><ttcol>Service</ttcol>
        <c>Meet and Greet </c><c>Sunday afternoon (250 - 350 people)</c><c>Cold appetizers, beer and wine</c>
        <c>Welcome Reception </c><c>Sunday evening (600 - 800 people)</c><c>Appetizers and cocktails (no-host bar)</c>
        <c>Companion Reception</c>
        <c>Sunday afternoon (20 - 30 people)</c>
        <c>Appetizers / non-alcoholic beverages</c>
        <c>AM Breaks</c><c> Daily beginning Monday (1,000+ people)</c><c>Continental breakfast</c>
        <c>PM Breaks</c><c> Daily beginning Monday (1,000+ people)</c><c>Light snack with beverages</c>
        <c>Breakfast</c><c> Daily (15 to 60 people)</c><c>Continental or hot buffet</c>
        <c>Lunch</c><c>Daily (15 to 70 people)</c><c>Box or buffet</c>
        <c>Dinner</c><c> Friday and/or Sunday evening (50 people)</c><c>Bar and hot buffet</c>
        <c>Bits n Bytes (reception)</c><c>Thursday evening (700+ people)</c><c>Appetizers and cocktails</c>
      </texttable>

      <texttable style="all" align="left">
        <preamble>Technology:</preamble>
        <ttcol>Item</ttcol><ttcol>Question</ttcol><ttcol>Response</ttcol>
        <c>Outside connection</c><c>Can we bring in our own external circuit?</c> <c>_______________</c>
        <c>Infrastructure</c><c>Can we use your cabling infrastructure to build a
        dedicated network, including installation of network
        equipment in data closets and phone rooms?</c> <c>_______________</c>
        <c>Access</c><c>Is it possible to have 24-hour access to data closets
        and phone rooms to support the network?</c> <c>_______________</c>
        <c>Wireless</c><c>Is it possible to deploy a wireless network?</c> <c>_______________</c>
        <c>Venue network</c><c>Would you be willing to disable your wireless
        network in the meeting and public spaces?</c> <c>_______________</c>
        <c>Infrastructure</c><c> Do all proposed meeting rooms have at least one
        available Category 5 twisted pair connection?</c> <c>_______________</c>
      </texttable>
    </section>
    <section anchor="flowchart" title="Contingency Planning Flow Chart">
      <t>
        This section is based on the Contingency Planning Flow Chart
        which is available at
        <eref
            target="https://iaoc.ietf.org/meetings-committee/venue-selection.html"
            />.  The contents of the link may changed as needed.
      </t>
      <t>
<figure>
  <artwork>
          -----
         (Start)
          -----
            |
            |
            v
    +----------------+
    | Does the IAOC  |     +------------+
    |believe there is|     |  Can an    |     +-------------+
    |an unacceptable | Yes | effective  | Yes |   Secure    |
    | risk in having |---->|F2F meeting |---->|  alternate  |----+
    | the meeting in |     |be organized|     |meeting venue|    |
    | the contracted |     | elsewhere? |     +-------------+    |
    |   location?    |     +------------+                        |
    +----------------+     /\     |No                            |
            |No            /      |                              |
            |         Yes /       |                              |
            v            /        |                              |
   +-----------------+  /         |                              |
   |    Does the     | /     +----------+                        |
   |community believe|/      |  Can an  |                        |
   |   there is an   |       |effective |                        |
   |unacceptable risk|       | virtual  | Yes                    |
   |  in having the  |       |meeting be|--------+               |
   |  meeting in the |       |organized |        |               |
   |   contracted    |       |elsewhere?|        |               |
   |    location?    |       +----------+        |               |
   +-----------------+            |No            |               |
            |No                   |              |               |
            |                     |              |               |
            v                     v              v               v
         -------               -------        -------        ---------
        (Proceed)             (Cancel )      ( Hold  )      (  Hold   )
        ( with  )             (  the  )      (virtual)      (relocated)
        (meeting)             (meeting)      (meeting)      ( meeting )
         -------               -------        -------        ---------
</artwork>
</figure>
      </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="log" title="Change Log">
      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="2016-01-12:">Initial version</t>
          <t hangText="2016-01-21:">Update to reflect
            https://iaoc.ietf.org/documents/VenueSelectionCriteriaJan2016.pdf
            and
            https://iaoc.ietf.org/documents/VenueSelectionProcess11Jan16.pdf,
            accessed from
            https://iaoc.ietf.org/private/privatemeetings.html.</t>
          <t hangText="2016-02-23:">Reorganize and capture IAOC Meetings
            Committee discussions.</t>
          <t hangText="2016-03-03:">Final from Design Team.</t>
          <t hangText="2016-03-17:">First update incorporating mtgvenue@ietf.org
            comments</t>
          <t hangText="2016-05-20">Updated in accordance with editing by Laura
            Nugent, Dave Crocker, Lou Berger, Fred Baker, and others.</t>
          <t hangText="posting as working group draft">August 2, 2016</t>
          <t hangText="Reorganized per Alissa Cooper outline">Work in progress.
            In addition, contributors were re-organized to be authors.</t>
          <t hangText="2016-10-28">Editor changeover. Further alignment with
            guidance by Alissa Cooper, Andrew Sullivan and the mtgvenue working
            group. Many various changes.</t>
          <t hangText="2016-11-16">Extensive editorial, format and polishing
            pass. A few substance changes, including food section.</t>
          <t hangText="2016-11-30">Additions based on working group meeting and
            off-list discussions; more editorial and format hacking.</t>
          <t hangText="2016-12-24">Various clarifying bits to provide some glue
            between the high-level 'objectives' and the detailed criteria and
            roles, per suggestions fronm Lear. Editorial changes, per 12/27
            response to Cooper. Refined uses of 'facility' and 'venue', per 12/4
            response to Carpenter; also added Carpenter 'lounge' text. Moved
            community consultation to a separate criterion; removed 'acceptable
            to the IETF Community from the 2 entries that had it. Removed
          Post-Seroul Revisions and Text Carried Forward.</t>
          <t hangText="2016-12-24">
            Address comments made on list by Stephen Farrell
            &lt;stephen.farrell@cs.tcd.ie&gt;.  Minor text change in Section
            5. Replaced links in sections 5.3 and 5.5 with <xref
            target="checklist"/> and  <xref target="flowchart"/></t>
	  <t hangText="2017-03-12">
	    Add openness comment as requested by Stephen Farrell.  Add
	    statement about 4071 as proposed by Brian and modified by
	    Jari.  Elaborated on what "unfiltered" means, based on
	    discussion between Eliot and Stephen.  Preface to Section
	    5 as discussed between Lou and Stephen.  Slight editorial
	    tweak to that by Eliot.  IETF operates 
	    internationally, as proposed by Brian.
	  </t>
	  <t hangText="2017-04-18">
	    Add new introductory text. Sharpen mandatory
	    definition. Split first criteria into two, and reword them to
	    be more actionable.  Remove net cash
	    positive requirement.  Change many critera from Mandatory
	    to Important.  Remove consensus text.  Modify chapeau.
	    Add some normative MUSTs in Section 5, and restructure
	    Section 5.5.  A bunch of other stuff as well.  Use diff.
	  </t>
	  <t hangText="2017-05-14">
	    Happy Mother's Day.  This version removes the tabular
	    format of requirements, moves mandatory requirements up
	    front, adds a desiderata section, adds a mandatory
	    filtering requirement, consolidates introductory text,
	    moves procedural requirements into Section 5, removes
	    the definition of Headquarters Hotel, removes the MUST in
	    late changes, and adds a desire for a local participant in
	    site selection.	    
	    </t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
